Off, okay. Today's דף *daf* is נ *Nun*, 50. Joe, welcome back.
It's so good to see you. Here, we have a seat right
for you here, Joe. Right here. What? Okay. All right. So we
pick up on דף מט עמוד ב *Daf Mem-Tet Amud-Bet* and we're
dealing with the whole issue about the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam, *Tikkun
Olam* around about collecting from grade A or grade B or grade
C property. And the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* said that for a כתובה
Kesubah, *Ketuvah*, she would collect from זיבורית ziboris. *Ziborrit*, grade C. And
the reason given is to essentially incentivize the men to get married,
that they're already that they're providing all these protections for their wives
and their כתובה Kesubah *Ketuvah*, we have to make it more manageable.
But
there
was a position of מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* who said that that
really is not true, that really the limiting of a כתובה Kesubah
*Ketuvah* from זיבורית ziboris. *Ziborrit* is actually only when she's collecting from
יתומים Yesomim *Yesomim*, from orphans, where anyway normally somebody would do it
from זיבורית ziboris, *Ziborrit*, but that when she was collecting from the
husband himself, it was a case of divorce, it was from בינונית
Beinonis *Beinonit*, it was from grade B. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is trying to prove this one way or another because it's
a very limited read of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, it's a very
hard read of the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*. Anyway, in the middle of
this discussion, without reviewing the point we made yesterday, although it's going
to lead to a digression today, but one explanation of a particular
ברייתא Braisa *Braitah* was that it was talking about not collecting from
the orphans themselves, which would have been from
זיבורית Ziboris, *Ziborrit*, not collecting from the orphans themselves, but from collecting
from an ערב Areiv. *Areiv*, from a guarantor, and that's a way
that we dealt with one of the with a way of dealing
with the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* that seemed to be a challenge on
this position. So within that context about collecting from a guarantor, we
pick up at the bottom of מט עמוד ב *Mem-Tet Amud-Bet*. So
let's take a look. It says like this. Yes.
Even an ערב Areiv *Areiv* or even a קבלן Kablan *Kablan*?
Yes, and we're going to discuss that right now. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ותיפוק ליה *V'teipuk lei* four lines
from the bottom on מט עמוד ב *Mem-Tet Amud-Bet*. ותיפוק ליה דערב
דכתובה לא משתעבד lo mishta'abeid, *V'teipuk lei d'Areiv d'Ketuvah lo mishtabeid*. So
one minute, you can't say that our משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, and I'm
not going to go through again exactly why we had to say
this was the explanation of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*, but you can't
say that our משנה *Mishnah* is talking about not collecting from the
person himself but from collecting from a guarantor because a guarantor of
a כתובה Kesubah *Ketuvah* is not does not actually become obligated to
pay. Why not? Because normally when I guarantee a loan, I'm saying
to him, look, you won't lend him the money. I will guarantee
it. I will co-sign as a guarantor and therefore you will and
therefore lend him the money. So since basically because I agree to
guarantee the loan, you actually took money out of your pocket and
gave it to him, and he accepted it, and all that was
based on my promise and my being a guarantor, that obligates me.
Okay, that sort of creates a sense of I'm indebted like it's
as if I accepted the money and so on. But by כתובה
Kesubah *Ketuvah*, no money comes out of anybody's pocket. By כתובה Kesubah
*Ketuvah*, it's promising without actually giving money, it's not like the wife
gives money and the husband promises to give it back. The husband
just obligates himself in the abstract. So since he's actually nobody's actually
transferring money on my say-so, you lack the mechanism and you lack
the גמירות דעת *G'mirat Da'at* for me as the guarantor to obligate
myself. Okay, so you could say, well, they're agreeing to get married
on my say-so, but we presume they probably would have got married
anyway, that that's not exactly the specific obligation
of the כתובה Kesubah *Ketuvah*, is not something that sort of I'm
taking responsibility for. So therefore the opinion the position is that if
I just promise to guarantee a loan, that technically doesn't really obligate
me.
You wouldn't really do it unless that guarantor...
Right, right. You're not going to lend him the money. And I
say I'm guaranteeing it. So fine, so you give him the money
and he accepts money and all that's on my word. That obligates
me. But כתובה kethubah, *Ketuvah* is just part of a larger package
of a marriage, and even if it's true you wouldn't have got
married had it not been guaranteed, which could theoretically be the case,
but the actual obligation of the כתובה kethubah *Ketuvah* is not something
that's taking place on my words. It's not part of actually money
isn't being handed over on my word.
Does the line literally say the the holdings of a כתובה *Ketuvah*
cannot be leaned through a guarantor?
Does the language? No, no. When somebody who takes who becomes a
guarantor on a כתובה *Ketuvah* does not become indebted, does not become
his property does not become encumbered, he does not become indebted. Right,
he doesn't become indebted. Right. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
how can you say the משנה'ס *Mishnah's* talking about a case of
an ערב arev *Areiv* and that's the case of the משנה *Mishnah*?
So it says בקבלן *B'Kablan*. And a קבלן Kablan *Kablan*, which nowadays
in modern Hebrew a קבלן Kablan, *Kablan* is a contractor, right, the
guy who... you hired to build your house or something. But a
קבלן Kablan *Kablan* is from the word לקבל *Lekabel*, to accept, means
that it's somebody that actually money changed hands. Now how does money
change hands in the case of a כתובה *Ketubah*? So basically here's
the way we would get the money to change hands. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* spells it out. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says שנעשה לה קבלן Kablan
שתפסה בנו מטלטלין metaltelin, לכתובתה והיא מסרתם לידו בתורת קבלנות *She’na’aseh lah
kablan she’tafsah bo mataltelin le’chtubatah ve’hi masartam le’yado be’torat kablanut*. So basically,
I'm saying to this woman I'm planning on marrying, look, here is
a pre-payment of the money for your כתובה *Ketubah*, okay? Here it
is, a satchel, a briefcase filled with $50,000. Okay, we were just
learning קידושין *Kiddushin* in morning סדר *Seder* and we figured out based
on the current price of silver that the current כתובה *Ketubah* is
because כתובה *Ketubah* now is 200 זקוקים *Zekukim*, which is a lot
more than 200 זוז *Zuz*. So 200 זקוקים *Zekukim* is now $27,000.
200 זוז *Zuz* on the other hand right now is about, depending
on how you figure it, either about $500 or $75. So okay,
which is why we've upped the value of a כתובה *Ketubah*. Anyway,
so I take this briefcase of $50,000, let's say I gave a
nice תוספת *Tosefet*, and I give it to my wife and I
say, here, hold onto this, this is a pre-payment for your כתובה
*Ketubah*, okay?
Now, now this is all part of a little ritual we're doing
in order to allow Michael to be the guarantor, okay? Because my
wife is only, this woman's only going to agree to marry me
if Michael's the guarantor, but here's how we arrange it that he
can accept that obligation. I give it to her. She basically says
fine, I am giving this money back to you now and it'll
just be a debt because you've already sort of pre-paid it, I'm
giving it back to you, it'll be a debt. But rather than
giving it straight back to me, Michael says, yeah, give it to
me and I'll guarantee the loan. So she gives it to Michael.
Michael now has accepted that money. He's a קבלן Kablan, *Kablan*. He
actually took the money. He's guaranteed the loan. And then Michael gives
it to me. Okay, but now Michael, because he accepted that money,
really does
become—no, give it to me right now. We're all going through a
little ritual here, but it's a ritual that makes you the one
to have received the money, so that debt makes you indebted now,
that creates the debt.
So if you lose it, I'm out if you don't pay her?
Yeah, yeah, because that's what it means to be a קבלן Kablan
*Kablan*. Okay, so a קבלן Kablan *Kablan* is opposed to an ערב
arev, *Areiv*. Now, in a normal loan, what that would be is
that the creditor, rather than giving the money straight to me, would
actually give the money to Michael. Michael says, look, Michael, you want
to guarantee that loan? I'm lending you the money. I don't trust
Dov, I'm lending you the money. You're the one that takes my,
you want to give it to Dov, that's your business, but you're
the one who's accepting the debt for
Dov. And there's even some opinions by the way that because a
קבלן Kablan, *Kablan* is the one that directly receives the money, that
the creditor can go straight to Michael without even first trying even
to collect from me. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* tries to work
that out.
What's the point of having you in there?
What? Yeah, I mean, because obviously I'm supposed to be the one
that's supposed to pay, but you know, but he's entitled to go.
Anyway, but we're not going to worry about that. Okay, so it's
a case of a קבלן Kablan *Kablan* and that's how we can
say the משנה *Mishnah* is talking about a כתובה *Ketubah* that is
being collected not from the principal, but from somebody else, because even
though כתובה *Ketubah* normally an ערב arev *Areiv* isn't indebted, this is
a scenario of a קבלן Kablan *Kablan*. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says הניחא למאן דאמר קבלן Kablan, אף על גב דלית ליה נכסי
ללוה משתעבד mishta'abeid, שפיר *Hani nicha le’man de’amar kablan af al gav
de’leit lei nichsei le’loveh mishta’abed shapir*. So according to the approach that
says that a קבלן Kablan, *Kablan* can become obligated even if the
לוה *Loveh* has no property, because presumably we assume that if the
לוה *Loveh* has no property, now in one way you could say
more reason to think the קבלן kablan, *Kablan*'s obligating himself, because it's
clear that he's going to be the one to pay up. But
you could also say that it's sort of like it gets to
a point of אסמכתא asmachta, *Asmachta*. You know, like, it's so clear,
like, I'm only going to be a קבלן kablan *Kablan* because I'm
assuming that I'm playing a role of a backup, right? So if
this guy has no money to pay and I'm not a backup,
I'm the one definitely going to go to, somewhat ironically, there's an
opinion that I'm less obligating myself, because then clearly I'm just asking
you to do a favor and lend the guy money because like,
you know, it's like I'm not, because there's no, it's not reasonable
that you're actually going to, he's ever going to really pay, he
doesn't have any money on him. So I don't know, I don't
really get it, but somehow if the guy has no money, it's
so much clear, it's such an obligation, a big obligation that I'm
accepting upon myself that it's seen as maybe I don't have a
גמר דעת *Gemar Da’at* for it. So if you say that a,
so if you, so it's less likely a קבלן kablan *Kablan* obligates
himself when the creditor, when the debtor doesn't have any money himself.
So if you say that's the case, אף על גב דלית ליה
נכסי ללוה משתעבד mishta'abeid. שפיר *af al gav de’leit lei nichsei le’loveh
mishta’abed shapir*, then I can understand. The woman's coming to collect her
כתובה *Ketubah*, and she can't collect it from the orphans, and she
goes to this person who was the ערב *Areiv*. That's how we
set up the scenario. אלא למאן דאמר אי אית ליה ei ait
lei משתעבד אי לית ליה ei leit lei לא Lo, משתעבד *Ella
le’man de’amar ei it lei mishta’abed ei leit lei lo mishta’abed*, a
קבלן *Kablan* only obligates himself if the original debtor has money to
pay up. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says I don't understand the scenario
that the woman is going to the קבלן *Kablan*. Let her go
to the orphans because it was only a scenario where the person
had money anyway. So מאי איכא למימר *mai ika lemeimar*, what can
you say? So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so now that's a silly
question in a way because Of course, so then after every single
case, whoever needs a קבלן, if a קבלן only obligates himself when
the original debtor has money, what's the קבלן'ס Kablan's role? And there's
an obvious answer. What's the obvious answer? What's the קבלן'ס Kablan's role
if a קבלן can only obligate himself when the original debtor had
money at the time of the loan?
If he doesn't have money later!
Right. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says: אימא דהוה ליה ואישתדיף. Eima d'hava lei v'ishtadif. He
had property but it got swamped or whatever and it's not enough
to pay the loan now. Okay, so this allows us to establish
that the case again in the משנה, we were trying to say
the משנה where the woman was coming to collect her כתובה, was
the case where she was coming to collect it from this guarantor.
So what's the scenario that she can collect her כתובה from a
guarantor? A, he's a קבלן, he's not just an ערב. And B,
the guy guaranteed the loan when the person had property, that allows
the guarantee to be binding. And now the woman's coming to collect
and the property no longer is of sufficient value. And therefore she's
now collecting from the guarantor.
That's that's the whole point of a guarantor.
I understand, which is what was bizarre about the question. ואיבעית אימא,
V'iba'is eima, כל לגבי בריה שעבודי משעביד נפשיה. Kol legabei breih shibudei
m'shabeid nafshieh.
Since it's said that the scenario was where the person guaranteeing the
loan was the חתן'ס Choson's father, so even though normally a guarantor
might not obligate himself if the original debtor doesn't have any funds,
but if it's the father, the father is willing to obligate himself
to his son more than a normal guarantor. Okay, so all of
that was quite, I don't know if it's confusing, but it's like
brought in a whole other area that we haven't even been really
oriented to. This idea of guaranteeing a loan in order to explain
the משנה.
And I thought it was also the the type of land, right?
בינונית and whatever it is.
Yeah, but we're bracketing that for... that was in order to deal
with the problem in the משנה, but now we're digressing to talk
about a scenario of a guarantor. Okay, so because the משנה created
a problem for us to talk about collecting the loan directly from
the principal, we shifted it to, meaning the principal borrower, we shifted
it to or the debtor, we shifted it to a case of
a guarantor. And then to explain how that works, we created a
קבלן and all these types of scenarios to allow us to collect
not from the person himself. איתמר. Itmar. Now because we're dealing with
this digression we're going to continue with this for a little bit.
ערב דכתובה דברי הכל לא משתעבד. Areiv d'Kesubah divrei hakol lo mishta'abeid.
As we said, a simple guarantor of a כתובה because no money
changed hands, does not obligate himself. So if he says, 'Yeah, get
married to, you know,' I say to the כלה, Kallah, 'Get married
to him, he's a good guy, don't worry, I'll pay the כתובה
if he doesn't have the money,' I'm just being... it's it's words,
I'm being I'm encouraging her to get married, but technically that's not
what the marriage is about and no money changed hands and I
don't obligate myself.
קבלן דבעל חוב, Kablan d'ba'al chov, the other extreme is a קבלן
of a loan. So on the one hand money changed hands, so
more the reason that I do... I would obligate myself. And B,
not only is money changed hands, I was the one that first,
I the guarantor, the קבלן, was the one that first received the
money and then I handed it over to the debtor. Okay, so
that's two factors to make it more of an obligation. Number one,
the creditor actually gave out money based on my word. And number
two, I actually took the money first and then handed it over.
Okay, so you get it? The כתובה has two weaknesses: no money
changed hands and it was an ערב and you know, I just...
you know, it was just a simple case of a guarantor. קבלן
of a of a loan has two has two strengths. Number one
is money actually was given on my word and number two, I
was actually the one to have received it first. So everybody agrees,
דברי הכל משתעבד, divrei hakol mishta'abeid, that does create
an indebtedness, you know, that does obligate me. Here's now when you
have only one of those two factors, that's less clear. ערב דבעל
חוב, Areiv d'ba'al chov, money changed hands, I said lend the guy
money on my word, on my say-so. So okay, money changed hands,
maybe that on my word, maybe that should obligate me, but I
never actually received the money. Okay, so that's one aspect. The קבלן
דכתובה, Kablan d'Kesubah, that's one thing that has one positive factor to
obligate me, but not both. Or קבלן דכתובה, Kablan d'Kesubah, a קבלן
of a כתובה where it's... it was כתובה so ultimately no real
debt was incurred, right? Remember I said we went through this ritual,
you know, the חתן Choson gave the money to the כלה, Kallah,
the כלה Kallah gave it to the קבלן, the קבלן gave it
back to the חתן. Choson. So in the end, like nobody wound
up with less money than they started with. Okay, so that's... on
that's a weak point about it. But the thing that makes it
more of an obligation is that actually the קבלן received some money
in the process.
Was it just a קניין Kinyan like of a pen or it
has to actually be a...
רש"י Rashi understands, רש"י Rashi understands that he's actually מקבל mekabel the
money itself. Okay, I haven't... I would have to review that, I
mean תוספות Tosafot refers to other parameters of what makes a קבלן,
but that's the way רש"י describes it. So a קבלן דכתובה Kablan
d'Kesubah has one positive factor to obligate me, money change... money was
given directly to the קבלן, but it does have one weakness. The
weakness is that in the end nobody really is out any money
right now, as opposed to a loan where somebody is right now
out some money. Okay, so in that... In that case איכא דפליגי,
ika d'pligi,
that's a debate. איכא דמאן דאמר ika d'man d'amar אף על גב
דלית ליה נכסי ללווה משתעבד, af al gav d'leit lei nichsei l'lovei
mishta'abeid, some say there there are cases where you do, where those
cases, those middle cases, you can obligate yourself as an ערב or
קבלן, but the question is maybe not in all scenarios. So, but
you can obligate yourself in those middle cases, but some say that
even if the לווה lovei has no money you can obligate yourself.
The איכא דמאן דאמר ika d'man d'amar and some say, אי אית
ליה משתעבד, if the לווה lovei has money you obligate yourself, אי
לית ליה לא משתעבד, if he doesn't you don't obligate yourself. Now
again, you ask me, it's a little ironic, right? If the לווה
lovei doesn't have money, all the more I know you're coming to
me, all the more I should be obligating myself. But it seems
to be that at a certain stage if he's that, maybe that's
seen as like an אסמכתא, asmachta, stupid אסמכתא, like I can't be
really serious because who, why would I ever directly be obligating myself?
I'm not just making my, I really just want to make myself
a backup. So anyway somehow that's seen as like too extreme, okay?
So in those middle cases it's debated whether I obligate myself even
if the לווה lovei doesn't have any money at the time. והלכתא,
v'hilchata, the הלכה halacha is בכולהו b'chulhu in all the cases,
אף על גב דלית ליה משתעבד, af al gav d'leit lei mishta'abeid,
even if the לווה lovei has no money I obligate myself when
you have one of those two, at least one of those two
factors, either קבלן or בעל חוב. ba'al chov. But the one case
is בר מערב דכתובה, bar m'arev d'kethubah, when you have neither of
those factors, both it's an ערב, so he never received any money,
and it's a כתובה, so nobody was, you know, was without any
money in the exchange. When you have neither of those factors, in
that case דאף על גב דאית ליה לא משתעבד, d'af al gav
d'ait lei lo mishta'abeid, that in that case even if the לווה
lovei has money, right, you do not obligate yourself. When it doesn't
have either factor of קבלן or בעל חוב, ba'al chov, then there's
no obligation is incurred. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why, now why is
it? מצוה הוא דעביד ולא מידי חסרה. mitzvah hu d'avid v'lo midi
chasrah. You were just doing a מצוה, mitzvah, you were helping this
couple get married.
Misleading the כלה? kallah?
Yeah, not misleading but like, you know, people making promises in a
way it's a promise, it's not a financial, it doesn't incur a
legal debt, okay? It's a moral obligation. You're saying it because you're
trying to help the couple get married, you're making a promise, you're
helping them do a מצוה, mitzvah, but because no money was ever
spent at that time, no money was given over on your say-so,
it does not become a legally binding obligation. Not legally, but you
still, yeah, there's still a moral obligation presumably. Now תוספות Tosafot, points
out, now this idea that it's a מצוה mitzvah is a new
idea thrown in, because until now all we were saying was nobody
spent any money and you didn't receive any. How does מצוה, mitzvah,
is מצוה mitzvah just trying to explain what the psychology was, or
is that part of the legal thought here? So look at תוספות,
Tosafot מצוה הוא דעביד ולא מידי חסרה. mitzvah hu d'avid v'lo midi
chasrei. תוספות Tosafot says תרתי בעינן, tartei ba'inan, it's only when both
are true that you don't incur an obligation. היכא דלאו מצוה עביד,
heicha d'lav mitzvah avid, if you're the ערב and it's not motivated
by doing a מצוה, mitzvah, what would be that scenario? דלא חסרה,
d'lo chasrah, even if no money was was lost, was out of
pocket, for example כגון שנעשה ערב אחר הנישואין. k'gon shena'aseh arev achar
hanissu'in. We already had the חופה! chuppah! So there was nothing motivating
you, say, come on guys, you love each other, get married, don't
worry, I'll promise, then you would have been doing a מצוה, mitzvah,
but we already got married! And then, and then after we're married
I'm saying, you know, I don't know, I'm having sec, you know,
I'm a little bothered here, I'm I'm afraid my כתובה won't ever
get paid up, and Michael comes along, and I'm the כלה kallah
in this scenario, and Michael comes along and says, don't worry, I'll
guarantee it. So you're not doing a מצוה, mitzvah, we're already married.
So in that case where you're making the promise and it's not
we can't explain that what's motivating you is just to encourage us
to get married, just to do the מצוה, mitzvah, well maybe, except
if the wife is the one that's having second thoughts it doesn't
do any good since the husband is the one that divorces. So
in that case, thank you so much Lennon, in that case it's
seen as that I really am obligating myself even though no money
changed hands. תוספות Tosafot, says אחרי נישואין או עביד מצוה וחסרה, acharei
nissu'in o avid mitzvah v'chasrah, which is obvious, if you are doing
a מצוה mitzvah but actually money did change hands, in those cases
משתעבד. The second case was the obvious but what was more interesting
was the first point of תוספות, Tosafot that until now we haven't
been mentioning the מצוה mitzvah factor. But since the גמרא Gemara threw
it in in the end to explain why are you making this
promise? Well, you're trying to help them get married. When that's not
the scenario, in the end the גמרא Gemara, says even though no
money changed hands and nobody was out any money your word was
enough to obligate yourself. I would, I would say that's very questionable
from the גמרא. Gemara I understand, whatever, it doesn't matter, I would
just say that's questionable. It seems until that line in the גמרא
Gemara that I needed something concrete to happen to create that sense
of me being legally indebted, right? I needed you to actually lend
the money because of my word, I needed to take the money,
I needed to do something that was going to create that real
sense of a legal debt, okay? And according to תוספות Tosafos just
סתם stam the promise after the fact is enough to create it,
which is a big חידוש chiddush I say. Like a קנס knas
on the... make that sense of me being legally indebted, right? I
needed you to actually lend the money because of my word. I
needed to take the money, I needed to do something that was
going to create that real sense of a legal debt, okay? And
according to תוספות Tosafos *Tosvos*, just סתם stam *stam* the promise after
the fact is enough to create it, which is a big חידוש
*chidush*, I think.
It's like a קנס *knas* on the guy.
Not a קנס *knas*, no. תוספות Tosafos. *Tosvos* is a question of
what is enough to create a legal—that legal obligation. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמר רבינא תא שמע ta shma,
*Amar Ravina, Ta Shma*. Now we finally, after that complicated digression into
the land of ערב *areiv* and קבלן *kablan*, we get back to
this question of whether the debate about a כתובה *kesubah*, whether it's
grade C or grade B, are we talking only about the heirs,
the orphans, or even directly from the בעל *ba'al* from the—from the
husband. And we finally resolve it by a very simple point about
the reason that was given for this for this הלכה halacha. *halachah*.
Okay, so let's take a look. תא שמע ta shma. *Ta
shma*—מעיקרא דתקנתין *me-ikara de-takantin*—from the very beginning of the reason we made
the תקנה takkanah. *takanah*, the explanation for this תקנה Takana *takanah* that
it was grade C. What was the reason we said that כתובה
*kesubah* is collected from grade C? משום דיותר ממה שהאיש רוצה לישא
אשה רוצה לינשא *mishum de-yoser mi-mah she-ish rotzeh lisa ishah rotzah lihinasei*.
We said the reason was, was because women are more eager to
get married than men, we have to incentivize men to get married,
okay? And if that's the reason, that it's about incentivizing men to
get married, obviously we're not talking about collecting from the orphans, that's
not what's holding me back, I would know that anyway, if you're
going to collect from my orphans it'll be grade C, right? And
that's not what I'm thinking about when I'm thinking about money I
might have to pay out. ואי סלקא דעתך מיתמי *Ve-i salka da'atach
mi-yasmi*, if the only issue of grade C is from the orphans,
האי משום דיתמי הוא *hai mishum de-yasmi hu*. The reason of collecting
grade C is because of protecting the orphans, it's not to incentivize
me to get married. דאי הכי *di-i-ha-se*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
תיובתא דמר זוטרא תיובתא *tiyuvta de-Mar Zutra tiyuvta*. So finally, after that
whole long complicated discussion, we said
of course we're not dealing with it's just being from the orphans,
because we explained that the whole reason for this idea of grade
C was to incentivize men to get married. So we're talking about
when the wife is collecting directly from the man, that the man
is only going to have to give grade C. Okay, so that's
the discussion around כתובת אשה *kesubas ishah*. On the one hand, all
of מסכת כתובות *maseches kesubos* is all about these protections that are
afforded to the woman during the marriage, ongoing responsibilities, as the marriage
terminates because of divorce or death, she gets this lump sum payment,
all of these protections, but sort of it's all a balancing act.
Yes, we want to give the woman all these protections, but we
can't make it so onerous that people are going to like, you
know, and we might think it's silly, you don't have to incentivize
people, but you do have to incentivize people, you know, and people
sometimes will push off getting married for a few years and so
on. You know, they did all these things about the שידוך *shidduch*
crisis, they found out that it's all based on demographics, it's all
based on the fact that because in orthodox—there's no שידוך *shidduch* crisis
in the חסידית *chassidic* world because people marry in their same age
group. But in the rest of the orthodox community, where men marry
about two to three years younger, and there's positive birth rate, so
every hundred men
that are like 22 year old men who are looking to marry
19 year old women, or whatever the ages are, for every hundred
men there are about 112 women. And the fact that there's that
difference, and they think that, oh, it's a buyer's market, so they're
taking their time and whatever, and that is the total source of
the שידוך *shidduch* crisis. So I mean, anyway, so the point is,
it's a reality. Sometimes you have to incentivize people, yeah, eventually people
will get married we hope, but you might have to incentivize, so
you're protecting the woman, but you have to make it that it's
not a—so that's the נזיקין Nezikin,
בור *Nezikin Bor*,
is that what you're saying? I'm just trying to once again explain
this רוצה איש *rotzeh ish* because you read this and you don't
really give it too much credence, I want to say it actually
makes sense, you're creating these significant financial protections for the woman, but
you have to make it that it's not seen as so insurmountable
that, you know, people are going to push off assuming those obligations.
She doesn't collect from the Mall of America, she collects from the
swamplands in Florida.
There you go.
Okay, so that's back to where we are, and that's why the
discussion is not by the orphans, but by the husband himself. All
right, now, אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן משמיה דרב נחמן *Amar
Mar Zutra breih de-Rav Nachman mishmeih de-Rav Nachman*.
Oh, that's good. Okay, I did need a
drink after that. שטר חוב shtar chov, היוצא על יתומים Yesomim *Shtar
chov ha-yotzeh al yesomim*.
Now, here we're going—now we're sort of shifting to the discussion of
collecting from orphans, and orphans, as we said, is from זיבורית Ziboris
*ziboris*, from grade C, and that's to protect obviously the interests of
the orphans. We'll see in a minute whether we're talking about whether
they're underage or even adults, okay? So he says, let's say you've
got a, you know, a writ, what's that called, the שטר shtar
חוב *shtar chov*, there's got to be an English word for it,
a promissory note? Okay, anyway, you've got this writ of debt that
is being brought against orphans, the father borrowed, you know, money.
Now, the normal הלכה halacha *halachah* would be you only collect from
זיבורית Ziboris *ziboris*, but here's the thing, אף על פי שכתוב בו
שבח *af al pi she-kasuv bo shevach*, the actual writ itself said,
you will be—I'm borrowing $10,000 from you, and you will be entitled
to have a lien not only on my grade B, because a
normal בעל חוב bal chov *ba'al chov* remember has a lien on
grade B, on בינונית *beinonis*, I am promising, I am giving you
a lien even on my grade A קרקע karka. *karka*. Okay, that's
what I did for you, or that's what the—that's what the debtor
did. And then the debtor went up and died. So now, is
he entitled to collect grade A קרקע karko, *karka* from the orphans,
because he was already given... Because he was already given an explicit
upgrade to Grade A. Maybe that entitles him to do it even
from the orphans? Okay. שטר Shtar. חוב היוצא על היתומים אף על
פי שכתב בו שבח אינו גובה אלא מן
הזיבורית. No, you have you still have to go down to Grade
C. That’s the הלכה. halacha. Orphans are always Grade C. אמר אביי.
Amar Abaye. אביי Abaye said: תדע. teida.
I’ll prove it to you. דבעל חוב דיניה בבינונית. d'bal chov dinei
b'veinonis. A normal creditor's entitled to Grade B. ומיתמי בזיבורית. u-meyasmi b'ziboris.
But when it comes to collecting from the orphans, he loses his
rights and it goes down to Grade C. So here too, even
if he was upgraded to Grade A, when it comes to the
orphans, it’s going to go back to Grade, he's going to go
down to Grade C. I know, it’s not much of a proof
and רבא Rava makes a very strong counter argument. אמר ליה רבא:
Amar lei Rava: הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of a comparison
is that?
בעל חוב דיניה מדאורייתא בזיבורית כדעולא. bal chov dinei m'deoraisa b'ziboris k'd'Ulla.
Let’s actually understand why it is that orphans get Grade C, because
why you collect from orphans Grade C, because from the תורה Torah
perspective, a creditor really is only entitled, even from the person himself,
from the debtor himself, only entitled to Grade C, זיבורית. Ziboris Why?
Like עולא Ulla says. דאמר עולא: d'amar Ulla: דבר תורה בעל חוב
בזיבורית. devar Torah bal chov b'ziboris. שנאמר: shene'emar: ובחוץ תעמוד. ve-hachutz ta'amod.
You're the one that is the creditor, you have to stand outdoors.
והאיש אשר אתה נושה בו יוציא אליך את העבוט החוצה. ve-ha'ish asher
attah nosheh bo yotzi elecha es ha'avot hachutzah. And the man who
you are pressing for the loan,
he'll bring to you the collateral outdoors. So it sounds like it’s
total, it's totally his choice what to give you as collateral, right?
You stay outdoors and
he, I understand, but it sounds like he gets to choose. So
מה דרכו של איש להוציא? mah darko shel ish l'hotzi? What's he
entitled to bring out? פחות שבכלים. pachus shebakelim.
He’ll bring out his most worthless object. I mean not worthless, but
it will be of the value of the loan but it won’t
be a high, like something that is in high demand. Okay, now,
by the way, as תוספות Tosafos points out, it's a little bit
of an analogy because actually we say that cattle, מטלטלין, metaltelin. is
always considered עידית. idis. It’s always seen to be as easy to
move מטלטלין. Metaltelin. By the way, do you know how, this is
going back, I realize, a few decades, but people remember the Shopping
Channel, one of those early cable networks? Might still be on. Anyway,
the apparently the way it started was that some
company was owed money from another company and the other company was
going out of business or something, whatever, and all they could pay
them with was like 10,000 widgets or something. Who knows? And they
said, "What are we going to do with all this stuff?" So
they basically just found a way to auction it off or
something, put it out on TV, and it went like hotcakes. So
anyway, so somehow it’s seen like cattle is somehow, you’ll always find
a market, is always considered to be עידית. idis. Okay, so תוספות
says it’s not exactly the proof of the collateral because that’s a
case of cattle, but what it shows you is is that the
debtor has the right to tell you what he is giving you
to pay the loan. Okay, and we’re going to apply that even
to קרקע. karka, So from there we understand that the דאורייתא deoraisa
הלכה halacha is is that the בעל חוב bal chov only collects
from the worst. Okay, so that’s the דאורייתא deoraisa הלכה. halacha. ומה
טעם אמרו בעל חוב בבינונית? u-mah ta'am amru bal chov b'veinonis? So
why did they therefore say that the creditor collects Grade B, middle?
כדי שלא תנעל דלת בפני לווין. k'dei shelo tina'el deles bifnei lovin.
For the obvious reason that you gotta incentivize people to lend money,
especially if they’re following הלכה halacha. and they’re not collecting interest and
the loans are getting annulled and all that stuff, you really gotta
incentivize them. Okay, but basically the עיקר דין ikkar din is that
they only collect from זיבורית. Ziboris וגבי יתמי אוקמי רבנן אדאורייתא. ve-gabbi
yasmi ukmi rabanan a'deoraisa. So by the orphans, we just restored it
to the תורה הלכה. Torah Halacha So רבא Rava is saying here’s
the reason this guy collects, a normal בעל חוב bal chov collects
from orphans from זיבורית, Ziboris because that’s really the דאורייתא deoraisa הלכה.
Halacha? So to protect the orphans,
we just go back to the דאורייתא. deoraisa. That’s in a normal
case. אלא הכא, ella hacha, but here, כיון דדיניה מדאורייתא
בעידית. keivan d'dinei m'deoraisa b'idis. If you
put in the שטר Shtar that you’re giving the guy Grade A,
you’re giving him liens on Grade A, then from a תורה Torah
law he’s entitled to Grade A. You’ve explicitly indebted yourself, you’ve explicitly
created liens in the document. So he מעיקר הדין me'ikkar hadin is
entitled to Grade A. So therefore, אף מיתמי נמי בעידית, af me'yasmi
nami b'idis, he should collect it even from orphans. So what רבא
Rava is saying is in a normal case, a בעל חוב Baal
Chov, goes down from B to C when he’s collecting from orphans
because he doesn’t have any explicit rights that gives him B. It’s
just that’s the normal process and that’s actually a rabbinic תקנה. Takana
So when it comes to orphans, he goes back down to the
עיקר הדין, ikkar hadin, which is C. But when it’s explicitly in
the document and he’s been granted the rights to A, then he’ll
collect it even from orphans. Yeah.
In a normal contract, I would have thought that if there's supposed
to be collateral, it would specify what it is, right? Does that
not come into it?
What the, what the liens are? No, the liens are on all
the real estate, all the holdings this person has. But you make
a good point, which is let’s say I explicitly wrote in the
document the Grade B land. So even the So as a בעל
חוב, ba'al chov that's not giving you more than you already have,
but now you don't have it as a תקנה דרבנן Takana D'Rabbanan
as a תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam now you have it because I'd
created those liens in the document. So that type of a case
רבא Rava might say the same thing, that that person would collect
from the orphans also grade B, right? Okay.
So then מצות אבות, Mitzvat Avot, I would have thought that means
the designate but no,
I understand, that's my פשט Pshat of a פסוק Pasuk but that's
not how we're reading it. Yes.
It's just such a clarifying statement that you made a few minutes
ago that there's always a market for מטלטלין. Right. You can always
move that stuff. Right. And get money, get good cash for it.
So why is the why is the foundational concept that liens really
are only for real estate? Like based on?
Because you can always find the real estate. Nobody can hide the
real estate.
That's why. That's why. It's always there. It's always there, you know
where it is to collect from. That's a okay. All right. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, right? That's the flip part
of it. Okay.
The flip out is the flip side.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so רבא Rava says that therefore if it's explicit in the document,
then the person collects the same from the orphans. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולרבא והתני, U'l'Rava v'hatani, but according to רבא Rava והתני
v'hatani אברם חוזאה, Avram Choza,
isn't this interesting? Somebody had the name אברם Avram in the גמרא,
Gemara not אברהם. Avraham. אברם חוזאה, Avram Choza, אברם Avram from חוזא
Choza or אברם Avram the seer, I don't know, אין נפרעין מנכסי
יתומים אלא מן הזיבורית. En nifroin min nechese yesomim ela min haziboris.
He says you can only collect from the orphans from the worst,
from grade C, ואפילו הן נזיקין, v'afilu hen nezikin,
even if you're collecting for damages. Now נזיקין, Nezikin what's the תורה's
הלכה? Torah Halacha A ניזק Nizak is entitled to collect grade A,
מיטב שדהו, Meitav sadehu, right? והנזיקין דינא מדאורייתא בעידית, v'hanezikin dina mide'oraita
b'idis, נזיקין Nezikin, are דאורייתא De'oraita entitled to grade A.
So רבא Rava says the when you get the orphans, you're not
going to go less than your דאורייתא De'oraita entitlement. So why נזיקין,
Nezikin the damages should be collected from grade from grade A from
the orphans? So the גמרא Gemara, says הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דהויה
עידית דניזק כזיבורית דמזיק. Hacha bemai askinan k'gon d'havya idis d'nizak k'ziboris
d'maziq. So we're going to have one of these complicated explanations, well
not that complicated, but whatever, you know, anyway, based on the סוגיא
Sugya we did the other day, when it says yes, it is
it is it is grade C, but there's a time even in
case of נזיקין that from a דאורייתא De'oraita perspective, you only collect
grade C. What would be that case? The case would be if
you פסקן pasken like רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, so the determination of
the best, מיטב שדהו, Meitav sadehu, is the best of the ניזק,
Nizak, not the מזיק. Maziq. So there could be a case where
you're only collecting the ניזק Nizak is only collecting grade C because
that's his best property. All right. So that's the scenario. He's not
going to come out ahead.
He can't collect from stuff he can't collect from
stuff better than his best field, than his best field. Meaning אברם
חוזאה Avram Choza is an exception.
Yeah.
So כגון
דהויה עידית דניזק כזיבורית דמזיק, k'gon d'havya idis d'nizak k'ziboris d'maziq,
the best of the ניזק Nizak of the damaged party was equal
to the was equal to the worst of the מזיק. Maziq. So
on a דאורייתא De'oraita level, he's only entitled to the the ניזק
Nizak when he collects, he's only entitled to זיבורית, Ziboris the worst
of the מזיק, Maziq, because that's equal to the best of his.
רבי ישמעאל דאמר מדאורייתא בדניזק שיימינן. Rebbi Yishmael d'amar mide'oraita b'd'nizak shayminan.
From a תורה Torah perspective, we determine it based on the ניזק.
Nizak. So therefore, that's case דאורייתא, De'oraita, he's only entitled to grade
C because grade C is the best that he's got. ומפני תיקון
עולם תיקנו רבנן בדמזיק, U'mipne tikkun olam tiqu rabanan b'd'maziq, but because
of תיקון עולם they entitled him to collect grade A.
וגבי יתמי אוקמוה רבנן אדאורייתא, v'gabei yasmi uqmu rabanan ad'oraita, it goes
back to the דאורייתא. De'oraita. So that makes this ברייתא Braisa a
very special case. The ברייתא Baraita. says even a damage even somebody
who's been damaged only collects from grade C from the orphans, and
רבא Rava says no, that's a special case when under דאורייתא De'oraita
level you'd only be entitled to grade C. But in cases where
the דאורייתא De'oraita level you'd be entitled to grade A, you would
collect from grade A from the orphans. Okay. So we're going to
challenge רבא Rava again. I mean רבא's Rava position makes a lot
of sense, but the the evidence is against it. So the גמרא
Gemara says איני, Eni, is this really true? והתני רבי אליעזר נבטאה,
v'hatani Rebbi Eliezer Nivta'ah, he's interesting names, anyway this רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer from נבטיא Nivtaya or
whatever, איני נפרעין מנכסי יתומים אלא מן הזיבורית, Eni nifroin min nechese
yesomim ela min haziboris, you only collect from the orphans from grade
C, ואפילו הן עידית, v'afilu hen idis, even if it's a case
of grade A, presumably that you're entitled to grade A. So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי אפילו עידית? mai afilu idis? What do you
mean you only collect from grade C even if it's grade A?
What's that mean? אלא לאו אף על גב דכתיב עידית בשטרא, Ela
lav af al gav dechtiv idis beshtara, it must mean you only
collect from grade C even if in the document you're entitled to
grade A. An exact proof against רבא. Rava. גמרא Gemara says לא,
no. מאי עידית? Mai idis? What does עידית Idis mean? שפי עידית.
Shefay idis. Now I'm going to explain this line because for simplicity's
sake like תוספות. תוספות says שפי עידית Shefay idis means it means
that you could have great rich, you know, soil and that's עידית,
Idis, but right near the river, right near the water where constantly
is getting sort of like, you know, flooded by the overflow of
the river, that's not, that property's actually grade C, even though it's
part of this great fertile land. That's called שפי עידית Shafay Idis
like these sort of flooded parts of the עידית, Idis, that's a
regular part, so it says you would regularly put your animals to
graze there, that would be like known that that would be a
regular at the edges of the עידית Idis would be property that
actually would be grade C. So what actually רבא Rava is saying,
he's saying is you're always collecting from the יתומים from the orphans
from grade C and you can even the שפי עידית Shafay Idis
is considered to be זיבורית Ziboris, when you're coming to collect from
the orphans. Okay so we're still talking about a normal case, not
that עידית Idis was written in the שטר. Shtar What he's just
saying is included in the זיבורית Ziboris the grade C that you
collect from the orphans is the edge of the property of the
עידית Idis which is right by the river, which is also considered
to be grade C. Okay שפי עידית, Shafay Idis, which by the
way works just better in the grammar, that you always collect from
the זיבורית Ziboris even if the זיבורית Ziboris is עידית. Idis. Right?
What does that mean even if the זיבורית Ziboris, is עידית? Idis?
It means even if it's part of an עידית Idis field, sometimes
there could be זיבורית there. Okay. ואפילו מאי
אפילו עידית שפי עידית כדרבא דאמר רבא Va'afilu mai afilu Idis Shafay
Idis k'deRava de'amar Rava like a different teaching of
רבא. Rava. הזיק זיבורית, Hezik Ziboris, if you damaged the person's grade
C land, גובה מן העידית, Goveh min ha'Idis, he collects grade A,
that's the הלכה, Halacha, right? ניזק Nizak collects from grade A. שפי
עידית, Shafay Idis, however,
if you damaged his
שפי
עידית Shafay Idis which is this stuff by the river, that is
not, that's even less than grade C, that's grade C minus, that's
grade D. And in that case, גובה מן הבינונית, Goveh min haBeinonis,
he's not entitled to collect from grade A. Normally a ניזק Nizak
always collects from grade A, even if you damaged grade C. But
if you damaged this שפי עידית Shafay Idis that is so worthless
that that's only that that you can only collect from middle level,
from grade B. That's רבא's Rava's opinion, which is so bizarre like
yeah I mean whatever I can't speak to it. וגבי יתמי אוקמוה
רבנן אדאורייתא. Vegabei yasmi okmuha rabanan a'de'oraisa.
Anyway so back to the point, so the point is is that
when it says you collect from the you know from the יתומים
you collect from the זיבורית, it means whether that זיבורית is standard
זיבורית or whether that זיבורית is C minus זיבורית, the שפי עידית,
Shafay Idis, that's what you're collecting from the orphans. Okay but bottom
line is, all of the evidence is against רבא. Rava. רבא'ס Rava's
סברא Svara makes a lot of sense. רבא Rava says it's not
a special תקנה Takana that we're going to downgrade all debts and
only allow them to collect from from you know and from grade
C from the orphans. What we're going to say is to protect
the orphans we're going to go back to the תורה Torah הלכה
halacha which says that these debts should really only be collected from
grade C. But if there's a case where the תורה Torah הלכה
halacha allows them to be collected from grade A like it's written
explicitly in the שטר Shtar or it's a case of damages, then
רבא Rava would say you could collect that from the orphans as
well. Okay, so you understand the סברא, Svara, all of the evidence
is against it. רבא Rava finds a way to re-read those ברייתות,
Braisos, but the simple sense of those ברייתות Braisos is it doesn't
matter what you're entitled to מדאורייתא. mi-de'oraisa. We're going to protect the
orphans and we're just going to give you grade C regardless. So
even if the שטר says grade A, even if it's a case
of מזיק, Mazik, meaning אביי'ס Abaye's position is, רבא'ס Rava's position is
all we did for the orphans was we reverted it to the
דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Okay? And in cases when דאורייתא de'oraisa you're entitled to
more, you would get it from the orphans. Whereas אביי Abaye says
no, no matter what you're entitled to דאורייתא, de'oraisa, for the orphans
we only allow you to collect grade C. So that's the basic
debate of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. So let's take a look
now as the גמרא Gemara actually finally turns to the case of
the orphans.
So if you had something in a שטר then you know even
from orphans would that be binding?
I don't know, according to אביי Abaye sounds like I mean on
the one hand you say כל תנאי שבממון תנאו קיים, Kol tnai
she-be-mamon tna'o kayam, so maybe I don't know. But אביי Abaye sounds
like no matter how much you're entitled to it, we're we're gonna
protect the orphans and only give you grade C. Now let's look
directly at the orphan case. אין נפרעין מנכסי יתומים אלא מזיבורית. Ein
nifrahin mi'nichsei yesomim ela mi'ziboris. So now we've seen this debate of
is it because we're reverting to a דאורייתא de'oraisa or regardless we're
only giving you grade C? Now let's see some clarification. בעי רב
אחא בר אדא מי יתומים שאמרו? Ba'ei Rav Acha bar Adda mi
yesomim she'amru?
So this keep raises this question: קטנים Ketanim או אפילו גדולים? o
afilu gedolim? When they said you can only collect from the orphans
grade C, are they talking that they're minors? Or are they talking
even if they are adults? תקנתא הוא דעבדי רבנן גבי יתמי. Takanta
hi de'avdi rabanan gabei yasmi. They look, they're trying to protect the
orphans. So לקטנים עבדו רבנן לגדולים לא עבדו רבנן. Leketanim avdu rabanan
legedolim lo avdu rabanan.
They do it for minors; minors their interests have to be protected
more; adults can protect themselves. So therefore it's only for minors. או
דלמא, O dilma, or maybe it's not really a תקנה takkanah for
the orphans, but it's משום דלא מסיק אדעתא דמלווה דמית לוה ונפלו
נכסי קמי יתמי דהוה ליה נעילת דלת. mishum dela masik ada'ta demalveh
demis loveh venafli nichsei kamei yasmi dehava leh ne'ilas deles. Here's
a meaning it's not like we made a תקנה takkanah for the
orphans. It's the opposite. If you think about fundamentally the case of
a loan, right? I'm lending money. Why am I entitled to collect
grade B? What did we say? That really I should only be
entitled to collect grade C. Why am I the The creditor entitled
to collect Grade B because we want to incentivize me, לא תנעל
דלת. lo tinol dalos. So maybe we didn't feel we needed to
incentivize me for the case of the guy dying. Most of the
time, I mean, obviously if I'm a good businessman, I expect, you
know, I plan for eventualities and I realize the guy might die.
But that's whatever, that's a rare case, I assume I'm gonna get
my money back before that. I don't need to be incentivized for
that case of the guy dying. So you only incentivize me for
the normal case when the guy was alive, you didn't incentivize me
for when the guy was dead. And that's why when I collect
from the orphans, it's Grade C, not a special תקנה to protect
the orphans, it's an absence of an incentive for me the creditor.
You don't have to incentivize me about that case. If that's the
reason, then even if the orphans are adults and they don't need
any protection, I just haven't been given that incentive in that case
and therefore I'm back to collecting Grade C. You understand the flip
side? Is it a proactive תקנה to protect the orphans and therefore
only when they're minors, or is it the lack of an incentive
for a בעל חוב ba'al chov, in that case? And therefore it
would be, and of course, a big נפקא מינה nafka mina is
what if it's not a בעל חוב, ba'al chov. what if it's
a case of damages, like we learned before? Before it said that
even damages you only collect from Grade C. So it's pretty clear
it's a proactive protection of the orphans, not just an absence, a
proactive protection of the orphans, not just the absence of an incentive
for the בעל חוב. ba'al chov. Let hold on the question, I
just want to see the answer, okay? Okay, תא שמע, I mean
whatever, I just want people to have the question clear in their
head. תא שמע דתניא בי כשישא, ta shma detanya bei kishisha, the
elder by it taught יתומים שאמרו גדולים ואין צריך לומר קטנים, yesomim
she'amru gedolim ve'ein tzarich lomar ketanim, even adults. Which by the way
is consistent with אביי Abaye because אביי Abaye from the previous סוגיא
sugya made it very clear that we have a
proactive protection of the orphans. All right, ודילמא, vedilma, the גמרא Gemara
says הני מילי לענין שבועה, hanei milei le'inyan shevuah, one minute, that
was the הלכה halacha that if you're coming to collect a debt
from orphans, you have to make an oath. The oath is I'm
making an oath that their father never paid up this debt. So
when I have to make that oath to the orphans, it doesn't
matter if they're minors or adults, they don't know directly the business
of their father and therefore I should have to make that oath
to them regardless. So that idea that I make an oath whether
they're adults or minors, that only comes to an oath. דגדול במילי
דאבוה כקטן דמי, degadol bemilei de'avuh kekaton dami, that even if he's
an adult, when it comes to dealing with his father's business, he's
like he's a minor. What does he know about his father's business?
So therefore I have to make a שבועה shevuah to him regardless.
אבל לענין זיבורית לא, aval le'inyan ziburis lo, but maybe when it
comes to Grade C, we're back to our question. Maybe I would
only do that for minors and not for adults. So the גמרא
Gemara says what,
what do you mean אבל לענין זיבורית, aval le'inyan ziburis, what?
Meaning for the idea that I would have to make an oath
when הלכות halachos apply to orphans, is it even adult orphans or
only minors? So if the הלכה is you have to make an
oath to orphans that the debt has not been paid off, the
debt you're coming to collect, of course it has to be to
adults because they don't know their father's business dealings. But when it's
coming to tell me that I can only collect from Grade C
property, maybe that's limited to minors because maybe it's a protection for
minors, a protection for the orphans and only the minors need that
protection. The adults don't need that protection. If it's been established that
the money is owed, right, is owed, so why do you have
to protect adults to not allow me to collect my Grade B
property? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והלכתא, vehalchesa, the הלכה is
יתומים שאמרו גדולים ואין צריך לומר קטנים בין לשבועה בין לזיבורית. yesomim
she'amru gedolim ve'ein tzarich lomar ketanim bein leshevuah bein leziburis. This idea
that the orphans is only Grade C doesn't matter if they're adults
or minors, doesn't matter whether we're talking about a שבועה shevuah where
it makes sense it applies to adults, even when we're talking about
collecting Grade C קרקע, karka, I can only, even and even if
the orphans are adults, I only collect from Grade C, I do
not collect from Grade B. Now I do have to tell you,
get to that in a second, that the logic of that in
the גמרא, Gemara I think I misstated it a minute ago, but
the logic of that in the גמרא Gemara is that it's not
a proactive protection of orphans. If it was a proactive protection of
orphans, it would only apply to minors. The logic of it is,
as the גמרא Gemara said, it's the lack of an incentive for
the בעל חוב. ba'al chov Since we don't have to incentivize the
בעל חוב ba'al chov? for that case, when he comes to collect
from orphans, even if they're adults,
he's only collecting Grade C. But if that's true, what would be
the case if it wasn't about incentivizing the בעל חוב? ba'al chov,
What's the case about נזק, nezek, right? So it doesn't really fit
with the previous גמרא because the previous גמרא said in the case
of damages, which is not about incentivizing the בעל חוב, ba'al chov
we also only let him collect Grade C. So these גמרות Gemaros
don't seem to totally be working in sync. One, the earlier גמרא
that applied it to a case of damages, seemed to be it
was a proactive protection of the orphans, but this גמרא saying if
that was the case, it would only apply to minors. So this
what?
דגדול במילי דאבוה כקטן דמי. degadol bemilei de'avuh kekaton dami.
That's by the שבועה. shevuah. That's by the שבועה. shevuah. So this
גמרא is saying that if it was a proactive protection of the
orphans, it would only apply to minors, and but it seems from
the previous גמרא that's what it was because it applied even to
a case of damages. But this גמרא's saying it's the absence of
an incentive for the case of בעל חוב baal chov and therefore
at least at least in the case of בעל חוב he doesn't
collect even if it's adult orphans, he only collects from grade C.
Yeah, I understand like the scope of this. Is this only in
a case where the loan became due after the guy died and
then he's just swearing that he didn't already collect and pay earlier?
Or is it like let's say this has been a court case
for years and then he was procrastinating and then he died, and
then am I still only entitled to like you know grade C
even though it's totally...
Whoa, no, no, the idea that the guy might have paid was
you know there are some exceptions to that that where it's clear
from events during the guy's life that it hadn't been paid that
that could exempt me from a שבועה. shvuah. That's true. Okay. But
the case about the grade C,
that wouldn't matter, I mean you know. I mean they're just saying
like what does it mean to protect the orphans? Once it's been,
I mean there's a question that I've got, like if it's the
lack of providing me an incentive in that case, okay, whatever, you
didn't provide me the incentive we're back to the עיקר הדין ikar
hadin that I only collect grade C. But if it's protecting, why
do the orphans have to be protected? If I had to make
a שבועה shvuah and once it's been proven that the money really
is owed to me, right, so unless the feeling is like look,
even if it's grade B קרקע, karka maybe I can, you know
there's different types of grade B. A lot of things could be
rated grade B and some could be much better than others. So
you know there's still a concern that you'll take and even if
the orphans have some type of an אפוטרופוס, apotropus, right, they're still
not handling their own affairs. So maybe there's some concern that you'll
take advantage. But if you're only collecting from within the range of
grade C קרקע, karka, there's less opportunity to take advantage.
But as an אפוטרופוס, apotropus, I'm just saying I'm hitting your point,
that's another words, is this again only when the loan became due
after...
I don't think that matters. What
difference does it matter?
Because then someone would just push it off.
Yes, yes, but hopefully the court system won't let the person do
that. I mean you're right, I mean you're right, that which basically
means what do you mean you don't have to incentivize a guy
for a case of death? If somebody is smart and knows his
business he thinks about those eventualities and he wants those incentives for
the case of the guy dying. So I don't know the answer
to that. But you're right, somebody might try to push it off
until he dies and then at least protect his orphans in this
way, I don't know. Okay, אין נפרעין מנכסים משועבדים במקום שיש בני
חורין. Ein nifrahin minechasim meshubadim bimkom sheyesh bnei chorin.
Finally now we move to another stage of the משנה, which is,
I mean we're still just about collecting debt, which is about that
you could you cannot collect from encumbered property that's been sold to
a third party as long as the debtor has actually still property
under his name. Don't go to any third party who was sold
to as long as you can, it means on you first have
to try to collect any assets that the person might still have.
Okay, even if they're we're going to see of lower quality. So
I'm a creditor, I'm entitled to grade B, Michael here sold off
all of his grade B קרקע to someone else. I want that
grade B קרקע, but it doesn't matter if he still has grade
C, I have to collect straight from Michael. Okay, so let's take
a look.
So בעא מיניה רב אחא דובוי בר אמי, Ba'a minei Rav Acha
d'vei bar Ami, so this רב אחא דובוי בר אמי Rav Acha
d'vei bar Ami is still asking questions and here's what he asks.
במתנה היכא? B'matana heicha? Let's say Michael doesn't sell his grade B
property, he gives it away. Okay, so what's the story? So why
can't I collect that grade B property that Michael sold that I'm
entitled to? תקנתא הוא דעבדו רבנן משום פסידא דלקוחות? Takanata hu d'avdu
rabanan mishum psida d'lakochot? Is it that the rabbis were saying look
Dov, you're really entitled to collect that grade B property, but we
have to protect people who buy land, right? People who buy land
can't be worried that that they're going to turn around and somebody's
going to seize it with a debt. So they need to be
told that as long as the person they bought it from still
has some assets they're only going to be gone to as a
last resort. That makes a lot of sense, right? If you want
people to buy land you have to tell them that this land
will only the the what do you call it the liens will
only be exercised as a last resort. If that's the reason, אבל
מתנה דליכא פסידא דלקוחות לא? aval matana d'leika psida d'lakochot lo? So
that's in terms of people buying land, but a gift? Gifting land?
So so since when do we have to do something to protect
somebody who's receiving a gift? All right, נבך, nebakh, you got a
gift and it might be that somebody will use his liens to
collect it, maybe we don't have to protect him. So maybe I'm
allowed to use my liens to collect the grade B from somebody
who received the gift even if Michael has property. או דילמא, O
dilma, or do we say מתנה נמי, matana nami, no even a
מתנה matana it's something we want to protect. Why? אי לאו דאית
ליה הנאה מיניה לא יהיב ליה מתנה. I lav d'is lei hana'ah
minei lo yehav lei matana. People don't סתם give gifts randomly. Why
do they give gifts? They give gifts because they received something. I
mean not necessarily it was not necessarily transactional, the person might have
been a good friend, he might have been whatever you know, but
it's part of the nature of the society in which we live
that these are things that gifts are given out of expressions of
gratitude of some type of a there's some type of a you
know of again I don't want to overly transactionalize it but there's
some sense that it's an institution we want to protect just the
same way we want to protect the institution of buying and selling.
There's some sense Some sense that you got something from this person
and you want to express your gratitude by giving a gift, and
we don't want that undermined by the fact that somebody's going to
seize the land. So
we protect not only people who buy land, we even protect people
who receive land as gifts. And therefore, even in that case, I
have to go to Michael, I can't collect, I can't seize the
property. פשיטא, Pashita,
it's just like a purchaser losing out his purchase, here too the
guy lost out his gift that to some degree he was entitled
to. So the גמרא says, so that's the question, does it apply
in a case of gift? אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא
לרב אשי, Amar lei Mar Kashisha brei d'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi, so
Mar Kashisha said to Rav Ashi, תא שמע. שכיב מרע שאמר, Shchiv
mera she'amar, a שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, a guy on his deathbed
says, תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני, tenu matayim zuz l'Ploni, give 200 zuz
to Reuven, ושלש מאות לפלוני, v'shlosh me'ot l'Ploni, and 300 to Shimon,
וארבע מאות לפלוני, v'arba me'ot l'Ploni, and 400 to Levi. אין אומרים
כל הקודם בשטר זכה. Ein omrim kol hachodem bash'tar zachah. Now this
guy doesn't, let's see, he added up four, three, and two is
what? Nine. This guy doesn't have 900 zuz, he's only got 700
zuz. So you don't say, well first give Reuven, then anything left
give Shimon, then anything left give Levi. You don't say that because
you can't say all those three words at the same time and
they were different amounts, right? So we don't say that just because
you mentioned one guy first means he's the first guy to get
the money.
וזה האחרון, V'zeh ha-acharon,
that'll be the next phase. לפיכך, L'fi kach, anyway, you divide the
money equally, even if there's not enough. Now what does it mean
equally? רש"י says, well what you do is, right, you basically say
there's, you divide it into nine units, and this guy gets two,
this guy gets three, and this guy gets four of the nine
units. Okay. לפיכך, L'fi kach, anyway, יצא עליו שטר חוב, yatza alav
shtar chov, גובה מכולם. goveh mikulam. If somebody has a debt,
money is owed to him and he's seizing some of the property,
they all lose out proportionately. It's not just that the last guy
loses out because the last guy is the last guy to get...
no, no, no, they all get it at the same time, and
if you have to deduct from the total amount, money that goes
to pay off debts, then they all lose out proportionately. אבל אם
אמר, Aval im amar, but if he said, תנו מאתים זוז לפלוני,
tenu matayim zuz l'Ploni, ואחריו לפלוני, v'acharav l'Ploni, first give 200 to
Reuven and after if there's anything left give 300 to Shimon, ואחריו
לפלוני, v'acharav l'Ploni, if there's anything left give 400 to Levi, אומרים
כל הקודם בשטר זכה. Omrim kol hachodem bash'tar zachah. If he said
אחריו, acharav, then you distribute it, you first give the full amount
to Reuven,
anything left to Shimon, anything left to
Levi. לפיכך, L'fi kach, יצא עליו שטר חוב, yatza alav shtar chov,
גובה מן האחרון. goveh min ha-acharon. It's only the last guy who
loses out. You understand why it's the last guy who loses out?
Because as the whole estate gets less now, you look at it
as that money was already owed to the
creditor, and now you first give to Reuven, then Shimon, if because
there's less because of the שטר חוב, Levi is losing out. Okay.
אין לו, Ein lo, and if there's not, and if after even
after Levi gave up all his property, there's not enough to pay
up the debt, גובה משלפניו, goveh mishi-lefanav, you go back to Shimon.
אין לו, Ein lo, and even if Shimon gave up all the
property he received, it's not enough for the debt, גובה משלפניו, goveh
mishi-lefanav, you go all the way back to Reuven. So that's the
ברייתא. Baraita So what we're going to see tomorrow, we'll have to
end here, is how that ברייתא Baraita is, because that's a case
of a gift, the guy is dying, right? It's a case of
a gift. And we're going to see how that ברייתא is going
to be evidence that whether in a case of a gift, do
we tell me that I can only collect from the principal, from
the person who actually I borrowed the money from me? Or am
I even entitled in a case of a gift to collect from
the land that was sold, even if the person, the original person
has money, has assets to his name? So we'll pick up with
that tomorrow.